[Music]
benita it's really great to have you on
this channel we've met and spoken about
these kind of topics a few times before
and we're we've just started a new
series called the collective
intelligence series and there's a lot of
really interesting work being done in
this area and I really like you sent me
a note kind of looking at kind of
there's lots of different definitions so
the word collective intelligence is
often used maybe in precisely offer many
different types of intelligence and I
know that you specialize particularly in
the one that I'm most interested in
which is a kind of an emergent group
practice and and creating a kind of
collective intelligence that's more than
the sum of its parts but maybe we can
just outline what what the distinctions
are and how the term is sometimes used
before we go into the particulars of
that kind of collective intelligence
yeah thanks for having me you know it's
a big field and there's a lot of
different experiments going on which is
really exciting but for me I think it's
probably timely to try to make sense of
some of the conceptual territory because
we're starting to get people dialoguing
and the contexts are slipping and this
always creates tension then disagreement
and it would be really disastrous if the
field split up along these lines that
are just definitional so so I thought
that was important for me anyways to
start with and you know I was thinking
about this and I was thinking like
collective intelligence is the word
you're using for broadly defined and I
was thinking if like we were aliens on
another planet and we were watching like
people from like a petri dish we we
would say wow there's so much collective
intelligence you know in fact over the
history of our species our geo social
spaces have become more and more unified
more and more systematic more more
interdependent more and more collective
intelligence fewer you know we have used
tries now we only need only have a
handful of Nations we have a lot of
trading currencies now we only really
have one neoliberal global market so
from that perspective we've done this
beautiful quote-unquote job of excelling
at collective intelligence and it
actually scares us now right because we
know if society or civilization breaks
down none of us know how to do anything
without being part of this collective
system this collectively ongoing system
yeah I really liked in the message you
sent the idea of no one knows how to
build an airplane that was a really good
example of what that means what that
kind of almost like would you would you
describe that as swarm intelligence yes
so the term we would use could use a
swarm intelligence or hive mind and you
know some of the people doing work in
this field throw that term out like
that's what the work is for as if we
need to put effort into that trajectory
the airplane metaphor I mean it just
just so could see them worse than that I
mean we don't even know how to feed
ourselves right or we don't even we
couldn't even grow our own food or make
our own clothes or you know someone runs
rope nobody knows how to make a pencil
right there's a lot of people that know
how to mine some of this metal or it's a
great get graphite out of wherever it
comes from and some people know how to
do the molding you know and and you can
go on and on and on oh look at this
thing I mean who knows how to build that
thing you know and more and more if you
think about it the trajectory of this
kind of swarm intelligence the
systematic operations of intelligence is
AI so pretty so even people don't know
how to do that those pieces that we know
how to do this
you know robots and AI will know how to
do it so this trajectory there's a lot
of momentum and you know I don't think
it's what we're talking about
it's not what we're all putting all this
effort into practicing right so I just
wanted to make that distinction because
early on in this work people were using
that as a positive kind of attractor and
so that's one distinction to be made we
can put that aside because even though
we have this collective intelligence we
might maybe say that we don't feel
particularly connected in terms of
relationally connected or intimately
connected or let a lot have a lot of
affection for each other right so we
have this collective intelligence but
we're certainly missing something that
perhaps we had in pre-modern times and I
think that's another distinction to be
made because some of these practices are
actually helping us reclaim something we
actually had a long time ago right and
and so that's still not an emergent
human capacity but I do think that they
somehow the emergent capacity in
reclaiming this earlier prior capacity
they are dependent upon each other you
said that that's not the collective
intelligence that you think is really
relevant so do you want to talk about
what collective intelligence you think
is the key one and what's your
background in that how did you come to
be interested in this kind of collective
intelligence yes so what I what I'm
going to turn when I use the term I use
for what we're trying to achieve a new
emergent capacity is collective insight
practice and the reason why I call it
that is a couple of reasons so we have
practice similar to practices that are
out there called the are called we
spaced practices or circling now
circling itself has a very broad range
of what people are doing so I don't want
to pigeonhole anyone but in general what
I've seen is that the purpose of these
practices
a lot of the focus is in processing
something like psychological or social
structures that are limiting right so we
have our social defenses and our social
triggers that limit authentic
relationship and we have psychological
structures that limit us being authentic
showing up authentically in in groups or
having transparent communications right
so a lot of the practices are at the
stage where we have to build the
capacity to D constructs or to resolve
these psychological or social structures
because they're limiting the way we can
participate with each other so that's
another level that's different than
collective intelligence it's sitting
down and kind of working on these
limiting structures that both are held
by an individual in a group so I don't
know to call that circling or we space
practices so those are practices that
are in service to the human individual
potential of the human individual so you
know I would I'm gonna say something
probably you know I don't mean it to
stick to all practices but a lot of
people my age know we see circling and
we spaced practice coming out of the
lineage of T groups very Carl Rogers T
groups and those also were part of the
human potential movement you know can we
use a group to potentiate the individual
and one of the things that was
interesting another distinction I'm
going to say is this comes along when
people start actually being able to see
the structures in society you know that
they that they're not pre given what was
happening is people started to be
actually see the structures that were
limiting them and first we saw the
social structures and people became
activists and you know there was all
these protest movements
almost the sixties and stuff so that was
a certain also a certain phase in this
work but the new phase is categorically
different and this is where I think the
new capacities coming online and the new
phase is we then were very frustrated
about the dysfunction in those protests
communities and the dysfunction in those
social justice communities they actually
enacted the same structures that they
were fighting against and people started
to realize that those structures were
interrupted in them and to me that marks
the modern age of these practices so
that you have to go back it's a it's a
it's more complex in order to change the
limiting structures that are programmed
by society you have to sit and
re-examine reconnect first learn how to
reconnect and then you have to work on
the fact that those structures are
interjected inside your own psyche and
so to me that marks and maybe you could
say in you know in language people
people are more comfortable with but
that marks to me the current new
emergent capacity of these practices I
just like to get a really concise
definition of what what collective
insight practice is and what it looks
like when when people are doing it so
collective insight practice is a
methodology for people to get together
and together come up with insights
knowings plans mental models ideas that
neither any of them had when they answer
together and it's not just some kind of
mash-up of clips that people had it's
something that if
sex people or seems to people as
entirely novel and new and they know
they couldn't have come up with that
without the participation of other
people they know even the crazy
nonlinear strings that they went off
with someone in an argument or in a
wacky humorous thing all these somehow
played a part and either disrupting the
system removing the energy or creating
new pathways for thinking in that
everyone has held a piece for this new
paradigm shift or this new way of
perceiving or new idea or new approach
to have arisen with that link I mean
what I'm what I'm hearing you referring
to relative to stuff that we've put out
on the channel before is the idea of for
example that Jordan green Hall and
Daniel shmatte Tim burger and others
talk about this game be civilization the
nun rivalries dynamics and what I hear
you saying is that we've internalized a
lot of those rivalries dynamics where
when it comes to sort of this kind of
game theoretical world or the game a
world we've actually internalized a lot
of these so where maybe the original
activists were also playing power games
trying to replace a system but actually
mimicking the worst aspect of that
system and sort of corrupt hierarchies
and is that sort of what you're what
you're getting at yeah no remember when
I originally was talking with Jordan
Greenhalgh at the time about this he
used to call it malware we're running
malware that's that's a cool term for
the introduction of these structures
right so and this is also why you see a
lot of meditation practices and
metacognitive types of meditations
coming online because you need a
metacognitive awareness to be able to
look in and see my god you know I'm
running malware I'm running scripts that
that are part of the
colonel system that that I'm running and
by fighting the system if I'm running
those scripts to fight the system I'm
just building continuing to build up the
system right so worse because you you
experience and probably you've
experienced as well this idea of you go
into environments where they say right
we're gonna get rid of hierarchies and
what you end up with is this sort of
underground subterranean hierarchy
that's far less visible and sometimes
far more pathologically enforced than a
clear sort of I mean in in in kind of
integral terms you'd say sort of a green
space rather than an orange space yes so
I agree with you and I think that you
know the the psychological process of
introjection is that then you project
the enemy oh and there's all these over
corrections and shadows and stuff like
that but what you're going to is an
experience that I had early on in these
practices you know I came out of
business and pretty dynamic companies
and then I started in being interested
in these practices because thought of
Sharma had written his books and all my
friends and integral were doing these
practices and the first ones I went to
were like oh my god like they're still
very over over facilitated and there's
all this manipulation going on except
we've been really good much better at
manipulating and I would rather have
someone just be aggressive or just be
you know an asshole then have that all
be underground and so it got gets very
very complex you know so people would
say everything is allowed in this space
and the next thing out of their mouth
would be let's only speak from our
higher selves and I'd be like my god 90%
of my experience it's just been
eliminated you know so there are all
these kind of interesting readings of
safety and psychological manipulation
and
Galit Arianism but people really held a
lot more power and so these things are
very tricky to be clear and clean about
and you know so a lot of the practices
that are that spend a lot of time in
just environment where there's not so
much cognitive or psychological
complexity help help liberate that also
just just a sort of backtrack a little
bit and why why do you think these
practices or these this concept is so
important yeah so that's a good question
I think it's important because first of
all I think there's an evolutionary part
to this I think we're doing the
practices because we're as a species
were changing I mean we we have never
really been
we've always been more social beings
that have been pre constituted by the
collective you know with with these
structures in us and only recently are
we realizing that we can be autonomous
individuals without being atomistic so
like if in this these are words on your
channel like sovereign if I'm sovereign
and you're sovereign then we have to we
have the advantage of diverse
perspectives we have the advantages of
unique diverse perspectives so as a
scanning collective were much more
powerful but then how do we put the
collective intelligence back between
that you know so we want to integrate
both of those we want to integrate the
power of unique perspective the power of
people with with skills and talents that
not everyone has with the power of
collective sense making because then I
think what you have is a problem-solving
methodology that we actually need to
address the
kinds of complex problems that matter to
us today I think that's the only kind of
dynamic system that will actually solve
the pickles that were in I was reminded
of Robert Keegan's work when you were
talking there of the idea of the
socialized mind this kind of evolution
from the socialized mind where we're
very much imbued with the values of our
culture and living those out in a sort
of more programmed way to the self
authoring mind and are you talking about
something beyond the self authoring mind
yeah so that's a very good question so I
know a lot of friends who I would say
you know they're all developmental stage
there is they're all certified in a lot
of the tests and some of them are
pioneers and I would say that most of
them have self authoring Minds I don't
know you know we can stop there but it's
really hard for them to have to act as a
team it's really hard work for them to
reclaim this team ship so we're not
talking about experts experts are
notoriously hard to get to talk together
we're talking about generalized
intellects at the self offering stage
who don't necessarily have the fluidity
or we don't have that the the capacities
or immediate skill set to go beyond
being what I would call individual
contributor so you know and and so this
is the experiments that I ended up doing
for five years here and learned the hard
way and yeah but but I think that you
know we learned some really cool things
about working at that level one of the
things we learned is that there's a
certain point at which that a
psychological processing you know that
that stage when you're you're trying to
get rid of you
own subjective structures and your own
limiting structures there's a point at
which that work can go two ways
one it can get exhausted because you're
just done I mean I've sat in groups that
are fantastically imaginative and we get
him into all these metaphysical realms
and it's almost like you're you know
someone will open their eyes and
everyone at the same time go holy fuck
you know because we all thought the same
thing at the same time but those realms
are infinite and I think this is somehow
some I think this might be how some of
the fantastic mythologies actually came
through because you start acting like as
a collective intelligence and you freed
yourself from even conceptual structures
and gets very very imaginative but there
was no purpose associated with it we all
agreed to disband and and try to take
this and apply it to action in the world
and in that we found that the action
piece is actually a significant
complement to the work like if you have
a group that does have a purpose you can
actually work on these inter subjective
limitations much more effectively than
if you're just trying to work on them
directly so a clear purpose and really a
lot you know this is you know if you're
a team with a work purpose even if it's
ordinary work you can really work on
these human potentials because you have
a clear worldly impact or worldly aspect
to it so my current work is people call
the guild craft or you know and it's all
about co-creating community with kind of
work for a creative purpose at the
center of it and so that's one way it
can go and the other place that can go
is I think that sometimes the people who
are primarily for
just on these psychological structures
the psyche itself is infinite and so
there's a point at which people create
new structures and then try to
deconstruct them and these things go on
forever so I just want to mention that
because there is a trap in some of these
communities where it's almost kind of
like appealing to have a never-ending
list of interpersonal problems to deal
with when you show up all the time so
this notion of knowing when to move to
what rehab that calls from the circle of
presence to the circle of creativity
when do you have to go from working on
your individual to as a group working in
the world and bringing some of this
early capacity leveling up in the
process so so that's kind of where my
work is at at this point and a lot of
its in organizations because there's
that work aspect you know you don't have
to pretend that there's a purpose
involved and it becomes less about ego
less about me and more about we and in
this sense I say that the definition of
a we is when the group becomes the unit
of agency right so a team is a week but
a political party is not a week because
it's more of us it's more of an identity
right so how do we take this work and
get to the point where it itself as a
group the dynamics in the collective
become a more powerful we that's can
transform then that can be taken and
transform the structures outside of
society and what you see is people then
don't go after the structures they tend
to try to co-create emergent structures
from within the society what happens is
that whole activist orientation to going
out there and top
something becomes what can we from the
power of this face through these
collective insights build and just have
that seed something new so you kind of
see you don't see it reemerge is a more
powerful activist coalition you see it
emerging like like a lot of the people
that are on your podcasting and your
YouTube channel they're kind of switch
to co-creating something new to a
collective insight rather than running
out in the world and attacking the
existing structures can you give an
example of what problems or what
situations you think are particularly
suited for this kind of way of working
and what-what are not particularly well
suited to it okay so I think two that
are particularly well-suited for it are
economics you know it's terribly hard
one of the limiting structures is what
is an economy without a global currency
what is an economy without currency that
can be traded what is you know so we
have a lot of its really really hard
I've worked with groups sitting here
trying to solve that and you constantly
catch yourself like you use the term
gift economy but then you're like well
when does it come back and you know
that's just a transactional exchange you
know so really trying to figure out what
is an economy without outside of what
we've always thought of as an economy
you know it's just like in the you know
before people could see outside their
religion it was just a given and we
think oh you know they're so silly how
couldn't they have just not seen it but
it's the same thing it's very hard to
see outside production in an economy or
production in a neoliberal global
conglomerate or some
so I think people are working on that
you know I know the people in home
watching part of their process is
similar to collective insight practice
or circling you know they use a lot of
those technologies to constantly try to
make sure they don't lapse into malware
you know to them now where doesn't slip
in so economics is one and then
governance you know what's got
governance enough in a post nation or
post state world the trick and
collective insight practice is you have
to invite other perspectives in because
if you only have your own perspectives
then it's really hard to come up with
any kind of new angles but if you invite
other perspectives in and everyone's
learned how to have really good
conversations then it's like when you're
going over a problem your own mind and
you're coming up with outside-the-box
ideas well you let others people's minds
also feel that that kind of platform you
know becomes a collective interweaving a
collective exploration of ideas that we
don't know yet yeah there was what first
excited me about the potential of the
the kind of intellectual dark web idea
was what King Eric Weinstein and Brett
weinstein on having a discussion about
and I think some of the lines or
something like those who a certain need
to be silent like we need we need and we
know that almost all of the ideas we
have will fail
we know that the socialist the
libertarian and the capitalist all of
these ideologies all of these fixed
methods are going to fail and we know
why they're going to fail so therefore
we need something new I think that was
that was a really exciting kind of it
was one of the first times I've heard
that expressed in a really public forum
like that so it sort of felt like there
was a possibility for this level of
conversation to really rise up and I
mean we've put a few pieces out recently
asking whether
that that kind of promise was fulfilled
with that conversation yeah I'd argue
that it probably hasn't been but I'm if
we're looking for and you also sketched
out the idea that we're having we need
lots of different perspectives is there
are there some perspectives that we that
we cannot include is there a sort of
trap of inclusivity okay how do we know
who who is able to have a generative
conversation and who isn't I guess yeah
so it's a very good question and I'm
gonna tell a story back up kind of
disentangle from this thickness and then
we'll pursue it so when I was doing
research on this stuff I I discovered
this very strange book called
connectives
and it was what I what T groups is to
search circling I would say synecdoche
the collective insight practice and it
was this weird exercise or practice
developed by these people I can't
remember who they were in the 40s and
50s and they were product designers I
mean they were all men it was like you
know at that time and they were creating
products like thermoses and you know
their tribe designed a better seal or a
better way for the thermos not to occupy
so much space so they were you know
pretty practical business and this one
guy right he must been a psychologist or
something he got the idea that he would
take his top designers and they would go
out to a camp you know they would get
out of their environment and they would
be in nature where they could think more
creatively and so and so what happened
was the camp being situation got more
and more sophisticated so they would
have to have the secretaries you know
bring the food and pack all the things
they would need and the secretaries
would come along to help support it and
eventually the secretary started sitting
in a brainstorming and they
would say things like wow when you get
mad like that you're just like my niece
and my niece is always mad like that
because of her like freaking you know
dish or washing machine and at first
people would like you know their
secretaries that's all they can
contribute but something they said would
stir something in one of the designers
like there's a he's got a lot of the
transcripts and so someone's like
washing machine and and one of the
designers started using his body like a
washing machine and be like yeah like
what and so these these weird kind of
like peripheral perspectives would act
as evocative ideas or phrases or
evocative objects in the space you know
so there was this whole cult
kind of they had to go and build a
department nobody knew what they were
doing over there because it got to be
like a big secret because they were
designing with this real really weird
way of using kind of like these
spontaneous impulses or intuitions or
felt senses from the secretary so then
you know later on people got really
interested in the idea of these felt
senses and these what I call
sophisticated naive questions entering
the space so I think all perspectives
are valuable and some of the juice in
this work is when a perspective comes in
and it irritates you but the person
sitting there adding these perspectives
has to be able to be authentic and not
be strategizing their belonging needs
let's say in the group because then it
won't be just authentic kind of
spontaneous who knows why someone's did
that and a lot of times in these groups
someone will say something else a I
don't know I'm just gonna say it but
there's like a cloud in the sky
and people would be like oh we know what
that is and then it goes around and
around and then a little maybe the next
day someone will say the cloud the cloud
in the sky that's what the meaning is
because we're thinking of the thing like
a solid state and it's really if we
expand the concept of the mental model
to some kind of face day and so you this
is why College really seems remarkable
because it's really like when you think
on a problem and then you go to sleep
and your dreams give you serve you up
all these potential ideas that don't
seem to make sense and then it can come
back together so this way it's a real
collective Co creative imaginative
intelligence and so all these kind of
strange ideas and irritations like we
worked with a group once and one of the
top people we were all like onto this
model we like so much and this one
person he was still a holdout he's like
yeah I'd like to go I'd like to go with
you but I'm just getting madder and
madder so this is a way of understanding
that even the negative feelings are
trying to manifest some other potential
in the space but of course this person
had high capacity to say that and not be
worried how it was going to live in the
space you know and and so we all honored
that in the ended up the next day
getting some clarity around some of the
assumptions we have been making so that
to me is collective insight practice I
think that I think it's I think as a
species you know we don't know how to do
this yet really obviously I hadn't
tackled and we haven't fixed any huge
world problems but I really feel that
the capacity for something emergent is
really coming online fast and for
example Jamie Weil who we've talked to
quite a few times says that where he
sees there
and I don't know if you'd say that the
word coherence is interchangeable with
collective intelligence in this context
but where he sees it emerging it's a
very unstable element that seems to be
breaking down very fast which is which
he finds very concerning would you agree
with that do you have the same
perspective um no actually I had a
little conversation about this notion of
coherence in these practices recently
and so I think I I think that the notion
the term coherence has something to do
with these practices but I think that if
you think when I hear Jamie will talk
about it he always then follows this
world word how is code how do we Co here
at scale and I think that's the trap
that's the old humanity and some kind of
big globalised coherent wholeness one
thing so I think coherence is far from
equilibrium it's by definition adi
stable or you know it's a temporary
stability and i think you know these
systems need to cycle through stages of
instability and stability and coherence
at different levels and there's a real
chance that all true coherence is local
and this has to do with entropy and how
coherent systems have to actually
increase entropy in the global scene
when you're talking about complexity so
then you can start to look at collective
insight practice say okay well that that
tendency to think of global coherence
for coherence at scale let's put that
aside now it's possible if we say
coherence only happens locally what
difference does that make and then
what's possible and when you do that a
whole new way a whole new paradigm
starts to open up and so that's the
distinction I would make with with with
Jamie and one of the you know there's no
evidence for this it's all very
theoretical but one of the things we do
know and
he's been part of the flow project is
teens you know when you do physical
things you can get this coherence right
but again it's local its local sometimes
to a teen sometimes it's just one or two
players on a team and so it there so
there's reason to believe that that if
we Rican sexualize coherence as local
that local coherence that seeds like
downstream some creative effects then I
think we're outside of a pickle or the
the way you know he's made an impossible
inquiry in some way that's that's my
response anyways does it make sense yeah
yeah that makes sense and what what
causes these these states to break down
but what are the sort of failure factors
for for the collective insight practice
I wouldn't use the term breakdown the
thing is why do we need these states to
D come here because that's only when
they decohere do they become action
plans and things that you do in the
world and now the world is gonna kick
back right and you can't have a group of
people that sit around and then cohere
the physical cosmos with their central
you know so so it's kind of like it's
kind of like coherence then you have a
new paradigm you go out into the world
you see it different the world brings
back information you come back with it
there's a whole exchange of and this is
happening you know the electron is Co
hearing and decoherent all the time and
face basis so when you look at this
stuff from a complexity science you can
get really comfortable with things
detail hearing and seeing it as not only
necessary systems property but something
that is actually advantageous I'm
thinking specifically about something
like Jordan green whole concept of
sovereignty that we can only really
enter into this sort of
creative relationship with each other
when we when we've established our own
sovereignty when we've established our
own ability to self-regulate and to to
do the work ourselves before we can
enter into these into these sort of
generative experiences is that a failure
condition or is that is that a sort of
necessary precondition for these kind of
practices yeah so for collective inside
practice it's a necessary precondition I
used to write you have to be
individuated to participate you know I
mean unless you're just recreating the
old structures you know so so that's a
whole other thing you know how what's
the difference between individuated
sovereign people in a collective space
versus social communal collectivism
right and so just ups the ante because
we want the autonomous perspective we
want the uniqueness we want the
sovereignty of the person but we want it
to be able to go here so the
intelligence is you know is accelerated
or not even in terms of velocity but the
intelligence that's capable is really
levels up to a different level but that
would still be local coherence you know
so if you didn't go here you would have
all meaning would stay open forever and
you would continually make and create
meaning but you know the convergence
onto a plan or the convergence onto
meaning making that you're going to try
out in the world these are all
decoherence States because now you hold
that and the rest of the world hasn't
participated in that so there's a local
coherence within the new kind of
interface where that's going to retest
itself and every time you add new people
in there'll be more perspectives and
more meaning making and so it's kind of
like stars being born and when those
star in nurseries you know the thing has
to blow apart to make make news
and so I just think that the the need
for the whole world to become here at
some level the cosmic cosmos is coherent
that's a given we don't have to help the
cosmos along its how to achieve these
human scale goals and you know what's
what's the optimum scale for that is is
an interesting question and you you
mentioned in the message you sent me the
collective insight practice is very hard
to do what why is it so hard to do yeah
so just the first capacity we need is
these to resolve these social
conditionings to socialize self so for
example a big one belonging me you can't
do collective insight practice if you're
if you're you have belonging needs needs
to belong to the group because those
needs those lower-level desires and
effects will prejudice how you perform
right so we don't want to change our
practices to assuage people's belonging
needs we want people to reflect on these
psychological structures that are
imputed a belonging need is deeper than
social conditioning it's a psychological
schema primary psychological schema you
know it's part of the individuation
process so that's why collective insight
practice is hard because you can start
with that one it's really hard for
people to get beyond that it's really
hard for people to get out of the
schemas of authority or roles or
autobiographical coherence you know I
have a psychological structure I that
makes me really important for me to have
autobiographical coherence this is going
to limit my participation I call it gate
keeping I'm not going to let it out into
this did you explain that I'm not sure I
understand what that means
autobiographical coherence in this
context so we can track the
primary psychological structure of
people over time and so at one point
people primarily psychological need is
for belonging and then the next need is
the role you know so the father and the
guy goes to work these are more 50s and
60s today one of the primary
psychological structures people have so
you become self authoring what are you
authoring your psyche a lot your your
that your your biographical narrative
now that becomes very precious to you
becomes another limiting structure so
with people are self authoring one of
the things you're working on is to show
them that the thought self off authoring
phase liberate but be careful that you
don't want coherent autobiographical
narrative because it's not true we
reconstruct that narrative
retrospectively so this will stop you is
that just just so I understand is that
that we end up starting to condition our
behavior based on a story that we tell
ourselves about who we are and a
limiting factor to collective inside
practice cuz you'll be one that is about
so that's why it's really I really
really well I kind of reminded of and
it's maybe a bad example but the
dialogue between Sam Harris and Jordan
Peterson got the sense Sam Harris is so
identified with this new atheist
position that the sense of an emergent
kind of any kind of coherence or a
synthesis that that I thought could be
implicit in their perspectives was
blocked because of that in my own
example
thank you so you see we know they're
highly we Intuit that they're highly
functioning they don't have simple
belonging needs and I'll polarize people
but they are dependent on preserving I
you know this autobiographical coherence
so this is a this is another powerful
structure it's one of the last one
well unless humans build more in between
but but that's that's another so all
these needs you you work on one and then
you get you know from Keegan's model you
develop but then you you know the needs
get replaced
they're usually easier and easier you
know the deeper needs are hardest ones
because they're just just I think this
is such a key point this
autobiographical Hey but
autobiographical coherence especially
when you have any kind of public profile
for example well this sense of and this
again going back to the sort of the
concept of the intellectual dark web
when I spoke to to Bret Weinstein at the
beginning he said all truths must
reconcile I think and there was this
sense of wow oK we've got a little
Jungian psychology over here with John
Peel us and we've gotten deep sort of
evolutionary biology over here with with
Brett Weinstein actually that there is
the place where they seem to link
because there's a concept of the shadow
and then we've got the fact that we've
got all of these kind of murderous
desires that are conditioned by
evolution there was a sense of wow this
could actually be a synthesis of all
these all these interesting minds but
what I think I've seen play out is that
all of these people with a public
profile and with a position to defend
are then so identified with that it's
very difficult then to enter into a
dialogue where you would have to give up
some of that auto autobiographical
coherence to enter into a new space is
really key point it is key and it's key
for people that are doing this work
because they're usually somewhere in
that kind of late-stage
psychological structure and you know I
just want to say in case they're
watching they also have a job you know
and they also are performers in a
certain way we don't know if they drop
that in and I suspect some of them can't
drop that in more intimate growth in
more local coherent approach
so but that's certainly a great example
of how it can be sticky widget you know
this this notion of autobiographical
coherence and I mean you know I teach
the whole course on what how the
structure has changed in evolutionary
development of the self and most of the
people I teach are right there you can
hear in my students they'll switch to
talking about the story they tell and
then they start to get very
uncomfortable because they can tell well
I could tell that story this way and
sometimes they tell it that way and then
they start looking for authenticity
authentic self like what is the
authentic self it's not even the one
self authors you know it's like you've
been snookered all along and now what is
you know and they discovered that the
earth something self doesn't have is not
a psychological structure at all right
so it's an evolutionary process or an
evolutionary moment in time so these
once you get to these distinctions then
retrospectively you see how and why
emotions and some of the ways you work
with emotions earlier on in we spaced
practice were actually also limiting
because you tend in many of these
practices we tend to accommodate needs
psychological needs of people and we by
doing that we're actually limiting the
potential liberation of that person
right so so that's when you get into
these spaces where people do less of
that and the more the energy is allowed
to enter but of course the more arousal
in the space the more difficult some of
these dynamics are to be present with so
there's always really tricky
so what does it look like it looks like
people well in my case it's more
powerful when it's in a nice setting
like my studio I mean you could do in
organizations but a nice setting in
nature is important it's also very
important and more powerful if you're on
site continuously for at least 3 days
and you eat and you sleep and you play
together now it creates exhaustion but
in the early part of the practice you
want people to be exhausted because then
they don't hold on so much to what they
know and they get into this place where
eventually they just like whatever you
know they're too tired
the organisms too tired to structure
itself and and a lot goes on outside of
what when we're actually sitting in
formal practice which is just sitting
around together with a time stamp either
enduring or enjoying what comes up
so that's what it looks like I mean I
have certain techniques that I do to
short-circuit some of these processes
now you know they are technique II but
I'll just give you one of them and maybe
you can do with it what you want but
it's called reverse bohmian dialogue so
Boni and dialogue is people sit around
in circle practice and you only want to
contribute something that's very
valuable or it carries the conversation
forward or that is in service to other
people or however it's set up and at a
certain point in some of the repeated or
sessions are done with no novice
practice petitioners if they get over
the hump the first day by the middle of
the second day I say let's practice
reverse bohmian dialogue which means
everything that comes up in your mind
you're just going to speak no more
gatekeeper so like you know we'll get an
idea and then
we can ideally I should hold off or give
an idea and we started you know so we
agree and you have to have everybody
literally orally commit to doing it
because if one person holds out it's
just not good but if you can get
agreement and we timestamp it so like
three minutes to give people the
confidence that they could enjoy this
because all they're thinking is oh my
god was gonna come out of my mouth and
what they realize is something truly
miraculous when you don't get keep the
thoughts they do not become disingenuous
and they do not become false and they do
not become arrogant or strategizing that
is an amazing thing like most of this
what you realize is the whole process of
keeping your thoughts and a loop in
yourself is what creates the damage not
the fact that you're saying it the fact
that it creates damages because you're
saying things that you've looped in your
mind but the spontaneously speaking self
with some kind of minimal agreement to
be authentic it's actually a wonderful
thing and that's a big learning that's a
big insight no filter you'd the right
timing yeah probably not a live TV
interview so that's kind of the
territory that is you know that I'm
looking it's been slow you know I
haven't done a lot of it lately because
I think that some of these challenges
like work that's being done in many
places are really starting to build
communities that that that can that have
capacity to to move on to maybe some of
these more difficult kinds of practices
and what he what yeah that that's
probably a good place to to ask what are
you hopeful about where do you feel that
the field is at now and where do you
think it's going and what are you
hopeful about I'm hopeful about people
making these distinctions at first the
field was well-liked nobody you know
nobody knew what they're really trying
to do
but he started off kind of with
assumptions that were not necessarily
helpful and where do I want it to go
well I would like to see more of this
kind of work being brought into high
level teams and organizations in some
organizations they are versions of it
are happening anyways you know the way
some really high level teams are work
together synergistically they're not
doing it methodologically but they've
worked through a lot of these challenges
if people who have a wicked problem
are already a team are already a group
it would be great if there was some way
in which they would find themselves
connected to people who could level them
up to maybe something more like
collective as I practice so start with
people already working pretty well on a
wicked problem that they're very very
gusted in see if we can get some local
coherence going right yeah and this
there's one one other question I'd like
to ask that sort of come up and that's
is there is there a gender difference in
this I mean you used a really
interesting example before about the
kind of executives and the secretaries
obviously that's in a kind of 1950s or
1960s context but I mean it's a simple
fact that most of the the people we've
interviewed on our channel around this
topic so far have been men and I I don't
know if I'm just not aware of the number
of women in this field but is there a
gender difference are there more men
involved because it would it would it
would seem to me that a lot of the more
intuitive awareness of the the kind of
the group space is something that women
are more sensitive to the men but there
are a lot of more high-profile men in
this area yeah it's a really good
question I have a long history with that
I when I first started doing this there
were people that are working with it
were convinced only women could do this
work that was before the distinction
the circle of presence in the circle of
creativity were made so women have a lot
more patience and endurance for the
circle of presence men tend to have more
creative energy but you can't really
bypass the the earlier you can't bypass
reclaiming these other capacities so
that was originally how was kind of
flushed out but I don't really believe
that anymore
women see there's like there's a
psychological there's a stage at which
you have a psychological structure I
mean you can call it an internal working
model in women's internal working models
are different than men's but you're both
internal working models and the way to
resolve them are the same so the fact
that they manifest differently is not
important and we spent too much time at
that level when we see they're actually
the same and they limit us in the same
way and where we're going to doesn't
have that caught mine anymore then you
just get over with it once people can
understand that then so women have
belonging needs men have ranking needs
they have to rank each other I happen to
be a Rinker that's why I'm on these
podcasts and other women are okay cuz
there you go but when you understand it
as the okay you can you unpack that why
why does that make a difference because
I like this kind of sporty intellectual
gain and I don't care if I belong to
your tribe or not so you guys like those
kind of people right so so we can all be
very happy we are rancors but it's just
as limiting as a belonging need in the
other Pro typology so it took me a long
time to I mean when I understood this
typology it was really liberating for me
but if you understand the psychodynamics
of psychological structures schemas
you'll see that they come at the same
stage of development the same attributes
and so you actually see instead of
talking about oh your belonging needs or
you you say oh here's our structure
again you know let's understand it it's
all the same so you see underneath
that's the same dynamic so that's how I
understand it now and all my insight
groups have been at least 40 60 or 60 40
I'm kind of proud of that because I
think the dynamics are really cool when
that happens now that's not to say there
shouldn't be separate groups because
they're also very valuable but I've been
fortunate to have a lot of a lot of that
diversity and had to you know we have to
look at that this distinction actually
came out in insight practice that sounds
like a fascinating distinction yeah so
how do we get more women on our podcast
I don't know I is not something we
should be aiming for in your view I
think it's something you should be aware
of and the awareness itself lends itself
to more positive behavior but I'm not
what I don't I wouldn't do anything to
more for your podcasts what I'd like to
do see is women doing more podcasts I
mean I've been asked to do podcasts but
I'm not a podcast person and and but I
don't know you know I don't know how to
really answer that I don't feel the need
for women to be on the kind of podcast
that they don't want to be on or to make
podcasts that they don't want to do you
know I just I just but I think it's
important in all these groups and to
your credit all these groups where
there's mostly men integral community
videos are non the same thing it's
there's a open awareness that there's a
lack of female representatives and
there's an ongoing search space without
defensiveness to support more women but
I don't have a problem that it just
falls out the way it does I just I mean
that would be a whole I don't know if
you can see I don't want to get into the
whole conversation but I don't I don't
see see the onus is on the side of the
person doing the podcast if in fact they
keep asking questions like that or are
genuinely open to yeah we just don't we
don't attract that slowly keep that in
mind until a natural way of doing that
happens but if you go overboard and it's
an overcorrection then it just goes into
shadow now you have the opposite problem
so it's a little bit of a pickle there
yeah yeah for sure but yeah this has
been really really wonderful Bonnie
thank you very much for making the time
I think it's a very timely subject and
this is a very very interesting
contribution so have a good night baby
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
calls to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews we're also
looking for talented people to help us
out with editing graphics music that
kind of thing and if you're a regular
viewer you'll know we talked a lot about
the value of embodying or actually
living out the ideas that we talked
about so that's why we run regular
events in London check out the links on
the website for more and hope to see you
soon
you